as we have been talking about HTML and
the origins of it and the dock type
element and I actually mentioned the
exclamation point that's in the doc type
element being a part of stml originally
and as well as the common element which
we haven't talked about yet and I was
reminded some time ago when I read about
this the drama related to this and to
understand this this is extra you don't
need to know this
but sgml which I don't even know what it
stands for
honestly uh what is
sgml I don't remember sdml stands for
standard generalized markup language
system for organizing and tagging
elements of a document allowing a
sharing of document formats HTML was the
basis for development of HTML and XML um
so it is the predecessor to it um it is
the thing with you know the angle
brackets and then the key equals back
pairs within those attributes that is
the that's the origin of the Syntax for
that um and I think it's a note that
sgml had you know one of its type of
elements had the you know the
exclamation point in front of it and
that when you see doc type and you're
like it looks different and you see a
comments and they look different than
all the rest because they have that
exclamation point that's where it came
from it came from HTML but I think it's
interesting to note um in fact I'm kind
of curious Which hat GPT has to say um
uh did uh does uh HTML 5 uh Implement uh
is let's see uh is HTML 5
implemented uh in HTML and my from my
memory Serv when I was reading
specification they actually broke ties
with it when they decided to change the
doc type um no HTML 5 is not implemented
in HTML although the earlier versions of
HTML were stml applications HTML
abandoned HTML and instead is using its
own par parsing rules which were
specially developed to handle the
various issues in contemporary web
development so most importantly the dock
type
element um was sort of mandated by stml
and that it if you see in one of the old
ones you'll see it it kind of links to
the
specification of the Syntax for that
document using HTML and you get this big
long annoying you know first line and I
believe I believe the reason that they
broke the primary reason for breaking
with um compliance with the HTML
standard was that line um and now the
doc type is is Doc type space HTML which
would be I believe a pretty blatant uh
violation of of HTML yeah Paula mentions
xhtml so
xhtml um HTML 4 all of the htmls before
HTML 5 which was created by the what WG
work working group and kind of forced
upon
w3c uh because w3c came out with the
extremely bad and totally failed
xhtml and HTML uh 4 versions um HTML 5
also brought Styles sheets by the way to
the world um so I mean I I can't even
remember the date but that's that's the
takeaway the takeaway is um anytime I
mention sgml with regard to H TL it's
because I'm old school and I I remember
when it actually mattered um and it
doesn't anymore so however XML is very
valid and there'll be a separate Video
Extra video about that about what XML is
why it matters so common image formats
like SVG scale level vector graphics are
implemented in XML still a very valid
very important format Microsoft Word
docs are in XML XML is worth learning
XML very clearly is an extension of HTML
so so knowing what standard generalized
markup language is is apparently
relevant still it's just not relevant to
HTML 5 any longer other than to explain
where that exclamation point came from
that's all